Guide to Voices of Crown Heights oral histories 2016.027
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Historical Society, 2016-2017; 2016.027.1
  - Lightstone, Mordechai, 2016 December 15; 2016.027.1.04
    Antisemitism; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Canada; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism |x Hasidic rite; Los Angeles (Calif.); Reformed Judaism; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Synagogues |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Weeksville (New York, N.Y.); Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Lightstone, Mordechai, Rabbi; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
  - Miller, Florence, 2017 July 27; 2016.027.1.22
    Seventy-three years old at the time of the interview, Florence Miller is an African American woman of Bahamian descent. She is the widow of a community leader in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her husband, Arthur Miller, was killed by the New York Police Department in 1978. A homemaker until that point, she had to vacate the building where her husband was superintendent, find work at a bakery on the Lower East Side, resettle the family, and be the sole parent to her children in another apartment in Crown Heights. After moving back to Florida a few years after her husband's death, she supported her ailing father, and later became a nurse with a focus in oncology at a hospital. She is a mother of four children.
    In this interview, Florence Miller talks about growing up in Florida, meeting Arthur Miller, eloping, and moving to New York as a late teenager. She speaks about the activities of her husband, their time in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and his death at the hands of New York Police Department. Miller chronicles the painful period of finding a job and working to support her family as a single mother, then moving back to Florida once her father became ill, and eventually beginning a career as a nurse. She mentions Arthur's job as superintendent of 925 Prospect Place, his emerging business in construction and building renovation, his grocery store on Nostrand Avenue (Bright Night Supermarket), the activities of the 4 Star Block Association, and more. Miller explains the need for the foundation called Arthur Miller Jr. - A Daughter Never Forgets, established by her daughter LoLisa (who is present for the interview, but heard only briefly). Arthur Miller (born November 30, 1941, in Nassau Bahamas, died June 14, 1978 in Brooklyn) is memorialized on the organization's website (https://arthurmillerjradnff.org/), and Florence Miller explains the non-profit foundation's mission. Interview via telephone conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community identity |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Florida; Police brutality |z United States; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bright Night Supermarket (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Four Star Block Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Jewish Hospital of Brooklyn; Miller, Arthur, Jr.; Miller, Florence; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; St. Mary's Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
  - Shaffer, Bronya, 2017 June 27; 2016.027.1.21
    Bronya Shaffer has been a resident of the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn since 1968. Born in 1948, she grew up in Montreal, where her parents settled after fleeing Soviet Russia. Her marriage to Rabbi Gedalia Shaffer brought her to Crown Heights, where she went on to have ten children. (Daughter Devora Shaffer was interviewed for the Crown Heights History Project in 1993.) Working as a stay at home mother, she also became a lecturer on Jewish life.
    In this interview, Bronya Shaffer talks about her parents' experience of being religious Jews in Stalinist Russia. She recalls growing up in the 1960s and how the Civil Rights Movement really grabbed her attention. Shaffer remembers her college experience, courtship and marriage, moving to the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, and encountering racism in the Jewish community as well as high crime in the area. Reflecting on the emergence of feminism in America, she discusses how those ideals affected how she raised her daughters and how this fit with the teachings by the Rebbe of the Lubavitcher Hasidim. Shaffer then relates her experience and some content from her time as an emerging, traveling lecturer on Jewish values, myths that grow out of Judaism, gender roles, and marriage dynamics. Focusing on living in Crown Heights, Shaffer describes the demographic turnover known as white flight and her feelings on security in a time of a rising crime rate. Exploring her memories of the lives lost and the unrest in August of 1991, Shaffer explains that city officials and the media distorted the events into a story of civil fracture based solely on race. She shares some frustration with how cultural institutions created further distortions in how they tried to mend the fabric of the Crown Heights community. In closing, Shaffer observes gentrification's effects and how rising housing costs make it prohibitive to raise a middle-class family in the neighborhood. Interview conducted by Svetlana Kitto.
    African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Canada; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Feminism |z New York (State) |z New York; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jewish women; Judaism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Religious identity; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Russia; Sex role; Brooklyn Children's Museum; Cato, Gavin; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Rosenbaum, Yankel; Schneerson, Menachem Mendel; Shaffer, Bronya; Shaffer, Gedalia
  - Simmons, Esmeralda, 2016 December 15; 2016.027.1.03
    Esmeralda Simmons is a founder and executive director of the Center for Law and Social Justice at Medgar Evers College. She is an attorney with experience in civil rights/human rights law and has worked for New York State and the federal government in law; clerking for a federal judge, serving as the First Deputy Commissioner for Human Rights, and working as a Civil Rights Attorney for the Department of Education. She is a Black woman, with roots in St. Croix, Virgin Islands, and was born and raised in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. She has lived in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn for much of her adult life. She received her undergraduate degree from Hunter College and her law degree from Brooklyn Law School. At the time of the 2016 interview she was nearing her sixty-sixth birthday.
    In this interview, Esmeralda Simmons speaks about growing up in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1950s and 1960s, describing neighborhood demographics, racial conflict, and her experience in Catholic schools: St. Matthew School, St. Francis of Assisi Catholic Academy, and St. Brendan's Diocesean High School. Also important is her description of the neighborhood, including neighborhood boundaries of Crown Heights which overlap with the present day Prospect-Lefferts Gardens neighborhood of Brooklyn. She also talks about her work at the Center for Law and Social Justice, the Black United Front, "The East," and Black political activity in Brooklyn (including electoral politics in the 1960s, 1970s, 1980s, and the era when the interview occurred). She also describes the decline of the neighborhood in the 1970s and her experience of gentrification in Crown Heights in the early twenty-first century. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans -- United States; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Catholic schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z United States; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Segregation |z New York (State) |z New York; Albany Houses (Housing complex); City University of New York. Medgar Evers College; Hunter College; Muse Community Museum (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); National Black United Front; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Simmons, Esmeralda; St. Brendan Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); St. Francis Preparatory (New York, N.Y.); St. Matthew's School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Uhuru Sasa School; Weusi, Jitu, 1939-2013
  - Suggs, Rudy, 2017 March 2; 2016.027.1.07
    Rudy Suggs, an African American male, was born in 1962 at Kings County Hospital. He grew up (and continues living) on Lincoln Place, between Albany and Troy Avenues in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. His parents were from North Carolina and came to Brooklyn in the 1950s. Suggs is one of seven siblings. He attended a variety of public schools as a youth in the Crown Heights, Gravesend, and Coney Island neighborhoods of Brooklyn. As a young man he was a drug dealer and spent eighteen months in prison. At the time of the 2017 interview, he worked as a cook at an elder care facility and served as a violence interrupter with Save Our Streets Crown Heights (based on Chicago's Cease Fire model), a program of the Crown Heights Community Mediation Center. He has worked with Save Our Streets Crown Heights for eight years.
    In this interview, Rudy Suggs narrates his life from childhood, to life as a young adult involved in the drug trade, up to the contemporary period where he works as a violence interrupter; all centered in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Suggs talks about the drug trade in detail and elaborates upon the 1986 New York Police Department 77th Precinct scandal. He describes his youth, being bused to schools that were predominantly attended by White students, and growing up in a large family. He also remembers the 1977 New York City blackout. He details his time spent in prison and how he moved from a life of crime to working as a cook for a senior citizen center and as a violence interrupter for the local Save Our Streets program within the Crown Heights Mediation Center. He also speaks about his experience of gentrification in the neighborhood. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Drug dealers |z New York (State) |z New York; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Electric power failures |z New York (State) |z New York; Ex-convicts |x Rehabilitation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hasidim |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Pillage |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism; Congregation Lubavitch (Crown Heights, New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights Mediation Center; Griffith, Michael, 1963-1986; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Suggs, Rudolph
  - Todd, Greg, 2017 April 6; 2016.027.1.09
    Aged sixty-eight at the time of the 2017 interview, Greg Todd is a real estate broker. He was born in Michigan and moved to New York City in the 1970s. He originally lived in the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn, then— still within Brooklyn— Prospect Heights, back to Park Slope, and then moved to Crown Heights in 2002. In 2017, he was staying with a friend in Park Slope as serious construction occurred on his newly purchased home in Crown Heights. He has worked in Crown Heights since 1987, first as a non-profit developer (with Brooklyn Ecumenical Cooperatives), and then eventually as a commercial real estate broker. He also is involved in urban gardening at the Imani Garden in Crown Heights. A father of two, Todd is also devoted to the permaculture movement.
    In the interview, Greg Todd speaks about the Park Slope neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1970s and 1980s, and the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1980s, early 1990s, and 2000s. He discusses Brooklyn Ecumenical Cooperatives and the housing conditions in Brooklyn in the 1980s and 1990s. He distinguishes between non-profit housing development and commercial housing development. He describes the role of city government in housing development and argues that Giuliani's administration eliminated the availability of non-profit developers to obtain city owned housing stock, instead selling it to commercial developers. Todd also speaks about his involvement in a community garden, Imani Garden, in Crown Heights. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Churches -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community gardens |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Environmentalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Real estate development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Ecumenical Cooperatives (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Community Board No. 8 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); De Blasio, Bill, 1961-; Giuliani, Rudolph W.; Harmon, Richard; New York Restoration Project; Park Slope United Methodist Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Todd, Greg
  - Workman, Reggie, 2017 June 9; 2016.027.1.17
    Reggie Workman, an African American man, is a well-known jazz musician who has been the member of jazz groups led by John Coltrane, Art Blakey, Pharoah Sanders, Max Roach, and more. He remained a touring musician at the time of this 2017 interview, but is also an Associate Professor of Jazz at the New School in Manhattan. He is from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania but relocated to New York City as a young artist. Workman was the Director of Music for the New Muse Community Museum in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1970s and early 1980s. He also lived in Crown Heights during this time period, on New York Avenue and Lincoln Place, Brooklyn Avenue and Dean Street, and in the Flatbush neighborhood (near Crown Heights) on Parkside Avenue, close to SUNY Downstate Hospital. He was living in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, at age seventy-nine, in 2017.
    In this interview, Reggie Workman talks about coming to New York as a young man to join the music scene; including his arrival in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, and later moving to and within the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Workman recalls the institution that was known first as The Muse, a temporary home for Brooklyn Children's Museum. He describes the genesis and content of the New Muse; a space that offered a planetarium and menagerie for children, music lessons, programming, and more for all ages— on Bedford Avenue between Eastern Parkway and Lincoln Place— starting in the early 1970s. He speaks at length about the kinds of programing that the New Muse organized and other musicians who were involved in the music program under his direction. As a result of political factions and decreased funding, he shares how the New Muse closed its doors in the early 1980s. Workman speaks about the community organization "The East;" located in the Clinton Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn and led by Jitu Weusi. He remembers life in Crown Heights, other organizations of musicians, and the drug epidemic in Brooklyn. Workman also contemplates gentrification. Interview conducted by Amaka Okechukwu.
    African Americans -- United States; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Museums |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.); Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Barron, Bill, 1927-1989; Barron, Kenny; Brooklyn Children's Museum; Collective Black Artists; Collins, Rudy; Crown Heights Community Service Corps (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); East Educational and Cultural Center for People of African Descent (1969-1986) (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Muse Community Museum (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Professionals Unlimited (New York, N.Y.); White, Chris, 1936-; Workman, Reggie
- Voices of Crown Heights oral histories: Brooklyn Movement Center, 2017; 2016.027.2
  - Davis, Alonzo, 2017 March 24; 2016.027.2.01
    Thirty-four years of age at the time of the 2017 interview, Alonzo Davis is a Black man and the founder of Just Been Tested (JBT), a mobile HIV testing and health screening unit and organization. The mission of JBT is to engage the community via innovative technology to become proactive participants in their preventive health. Davis was born and raised in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and went to boarding school during his secondary school years.
    In this interview, Alonzo Davis recalls life as a child growing up in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He describes his block and immediate neighborhood, contrasting those with his later experience at a boarding school outside of the city. Davis discusses his memories of some events during the 1991 Crown Heights "riot," and this leads into general observations about people in conflict there. Contrasting 2017 with how policing and safety has changed since the early 1990s, he invokes his own experiences and the observations of his father, who worked in the New York Police Department before moving up the ranks in Corrections. Davis also considers how neighborliness plays into a sense of safety at home. After a pause in the interview, he concludes with a description of the Crown Heights landscape during the crack cocaine epidemic. Interview conducted by Mark Winston Griffith.
    Activism; African Americans |x Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Private schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Davis, Alonzo
  - Finlay, Alisha, 2017 March 9; 2016.027.2.02
    Thirty-seven years of age at the time of the 2017 interview, Alisha Finlay was born in Boston, Massachusetts to parents from Trinidad. Many of her relatives settled in New York City, and her immediate family followed by relocating to the Bushwick neighborhood of Brooklyn when Finlay was still a child. Finlay's social life as a teenager was split between keeping in touch with Bushwick contacts while acclimating to her family's later residence in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Finlay attended Clara Barton High School in Crown Heights. A mother of two in her twenties, Finlay later needed to sever ties with the children's father; leading to altercations with him, arrests and advice from police officers, and encounters with the judicial system. In 2017, she was participating in local community affairs and held a position with the Union Street Block and Civic Association.
    In the interview, Alisha Finlay recalls her childhood, her teens, and feelings about living in the Bushwick and Crown Heights neighborhoods of Brooklyn; noting their differences. She refers to her recollection and understanding of the August, 1991 uprising in Crown Heights, as well as the secondhand experiences of relatives. Much of the interview turns on Finlay's experiences and evolving opinions on policing; on the level of cultural understanding and on a level of her personal encounters with police. That subject leads into her discussion of gentrification and what she favors and dislikes about its effect on Crown Heights. In closing, Finlay also notes the influence of the Hasidic community on the area. Interview conducted by Walis Johnson.
    Conditions Governing Access and Rights
    African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police-community relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trinidadian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social life and customs; Finlay, Alisha; New York (N.Y.). Police Department
  - Porter, Evangeline, 2017 March 8; 2016.027.2.03